<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2  Coprocessor on HW/SW codesign</title>
    <link>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2  Coprocessor on HW/SW codesign</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <managingEditor>&lt;i&gt;fname&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;i&gt;lname&lt;/i&gt;A T&lt;i&gt;kuleuven.be&lt;/i&gt; (Jo Vliegen)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>&lt;i&gt;fname&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;i&gt;lname&lt;/i&gt;A T&lt;i&gt;kuleuven.be&lt;/i&gt; (Jo Vliegen)</webMaster><atom:link href="https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>201 - Coprocessor</title>
      <link>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/201_coprocessor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>&lt;i&gt;fname&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;i&gt;lname&lt;/i&gt;A T&lt;i&gt;kuleuven.be&lt;/i&gt; (Jo Vliegen)</author>
      <guid>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/201_coprocessor/</guid>
      <description>All the code that you write has to be executed on the processor. With computers being ever more powerful, it is easy to forget about all the work a processor is doing. Irrespective of how simple a job might seem, it still needs to be executed. The example illustrates this. The only thing the processor needs to do is output 2 values. Nonetheless with the software as seen before, this takes 74 clock cycles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>202 - Pico CoProcessor Interface (PCPI)</title>
      <link>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/202_pcpi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>&lt;i&gt;fname&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;i&gt;lname&lt;/i&gt;A T&lt;i&gt;kuleuven.be&lt;/i&gt; (Jo Vliegen)</author>
      <guid>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/202_pcpi/</guid>
      <description>In Chapter 1 we&amp;rsquo;ve used the PicoRV32 implementation of a RISC-V. This implementation has a number of interfaces to the outside world. The memory interface was already discussed. In this section the Pico CoProcessor Interface (PCPI) is handled.
Multiplication coprocessor To illustrate (the use of) a coprocessor, let&amp;rsquo;s take the multiplication. In the previous section it is illustrated how the compiler jumped in to achieve multiplication. Depending on the factors, this might take a lot time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>203 - Coprocessor example</title>
      <link>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/203_coproccesor_hd/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>&lt;i&gt;fname&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;i&gt;lname&lt;/i&gt;A T&lt;i&gt;kuleuven.be&lt;/i&gt; (Jo Vliegen)</author>
      <guid>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/203_coproccesor_hd/</guid>
      <description>Coprocessor example As an example of a custom coprocessor a hardware component is made for calculating the Hamming distance.
Control path The control path is made with a set-reset flipflop. The condition for setting is determined by the pcpi_valid signal and the instruction. Only if the opcode in pcpi_insn is 0110011 and the additional opcode field (funct7) is 0000001, this coprocessor is targeted.
As long as the set-reset-flipflop is turned on, the coprocessor keeps on working.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>204 - Exercises</title>
      <link>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/204_exercises/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>&lt;i&gt;fname&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;i&gt;lname&lt;/i&gt;A T&lt;i&gt;kuleuven.be&lt;/i&gt; (Jo Vliegen)</author>
      <guid>https://kuleuven-diepenbeek.github.io/course_hwswcodesign/200_coprocessor/204_exercises/</guid>
      <description>Exercise 201 Try to get the example for the Hamming distance to work. Make a comparison like the table in 202 where you compare your pure software implementation of the Hamming distance with the codesign.
Exercise 202 Transform the Hamming distance coprocessor to work on the div instruction in stead of the mul instruction.
Exercise 203 Make a new coprocessor that calculates the average of two integer numbers. If the result is non-integer, round it down.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
